Fran: I think if we talk about witnessing
of abuse in the, in the childhood home
again, that comes back to the work
I do with carers being an issue with
young people that's a massive factor.
Witnessing actual family abuse is...
can be devastating to a person, even if
they weren't victims of abuse themselves.
I mean, I stand to believe that really,
if you, in a house where it is abusive,
then you are a victim of abuse in some way
Tamzin: If they've experienced it
or they've witnessed it, it does,
obviously, it does lie with them.
And we often find, we work with
young people that like you say
that've previously been abused
or they've witnessed domestic
violence in the family home.
And they're kind of struggling.
Like I said, they are
struggling to deal with it.
And like I was saying before, sometimes
young people come to our service when
they're not ready for support and they
disengage, and they might be ready a
few years down the line because they're
still trying to get over what's happened.
Fran: Witnessing bullying.
Witnessing things in school, I suppose,
as a kid, I don't know if that is, as, I
don't think it is as damaging, I suppose
it depends what you, what you witnessed.
If it's something you're
witnessing constantly.
I think that can have a big effect
.
Tamzin: Things, you know, obviously
like abuse and witnessing abuse,
you know, it's, it's trauma, like I
was saying before, and it's trauma
to the young person and it's trauma
for what they've had to go through.
And sometimes young people block it out.
So if they've gone through a period where
there's been domestic abuse in the home,
they might just kind of be switching off
and they might come detached from it.
And you often find when you might
be working with someone like that,
they are detached and the space
is not there yet to work on them.
Fran: Witnessing regular abuse, and even
one incident of abuse in the home, I think
is potentially lifelong and can affect
you for the rest of your life in some
way, if you don't get the right support.
So I think, yeah, I think it's huge.
Tamzin: And it's getting that support
for it, but if they're ready for the
support, 'cause like we, we always say he
might not be ready to work on that trauma
'cause it might still be too raw for them.
So it might be a few years down the
line that they can work on that.
And for now we're just going to work on
something like a goal that can help them.
So it could just be to work on them,
get into college more or, you know,
attending school or going to work.